[音乐播放]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
大卫·马兰：好了 这是CS50的S介绍
DAVID MALAN: All right, this is CS50's introduction
到使用Python语言编程
to programming with Python.
我叫大卫·马兰
My name is David Malan.
本周是我们的例外周
And this is our week on exceptions.
Python和其他编程语言中的异常
Exceptions in Python as well as in other programming languages
请参阅代码中的问题
refer to problems in your code.
事实上 当你的程序中有一些特殊的东西时
Indeed, when something is exceptional in your program,
这实际上并不意味着这是一件好事
it actually doesn't mean it's a good thing.
这意味着有些事情出了问题 理想情况下 你会设法解决的
It means something has gone wrong that, ideally, you will somehow solve.
那么 有哪些事情可能会出错呢？
So what are some of the things that can go wrong?
因此 我将继续在我的计算机上打开VS Code
So I'm going to go ahead and open up VS Code on my computer here.
在终端窗口中 我将继续运行hello.py的代码
And in the terminal window, I'm going to go ahead and run code of hello.py.
当然 这将开启一个品牌
That's going to, of course, open up a brand
我的新选项卡hello.py 我可以在其中编写代码
new tab for me, hello.py, in which I can write my code.
让我继续编写一些非常简单的代码
And let me go ahead and write some very simple code just
向世界问好
to say hello to the world.
让我们来打个招呼：“你好 世界
Let's go ahead and say print "hello, world.
然后让我继续 然后--
And then let me go ahead and--
我忘了结束那句引语了
I'm forgetting to close that quote.
所以你自己可能已经犯了一个错误
So a mistake that you yourself might have already made
或者肯定会在未来制造--这有点微妙
or might surely in the future make-- and it's a little subtle
因为你可能不一定会注意到你刚刚
because you might not necessarily notice that you've just
错过了这一个角色
missed that one character.
好吧 让我乐观地说下去
Well, let me go ahead and somewhat optimistically
现在转到我的终端窗口 运行hello.py的Python并按Enter键
go down to my terminal window now and run Python of hello.py and hit Enter.
这是我犯的第一个错误
And that's the first of my errors.
天哪 我只写了一行代码
My gosh, I've only written one line of code.
而且我的屏幕上似乎有更多的错误行
And I seem to have more lines of errors on the screen.
但突出的一点是这里最底层的东西
But the salient point is this bottom-most thing here.
请注意它显示语法错误的位置
Notice where it says syntax error.
语法错误是您键入的代码、您的语法有问题
A syntax error is a problem with the code that you have typed, your syntax.
就像英语和其他人类语言一样
Just like English and other human languages
有与之相关的语法 我的代码也是如此
have syntax associated with them, so does my code.
而且这并不完全正确
And it's not quite correct.
有些事不对劲
Something is awry.
我没有完全按照指示去做
I didn't follow the instructions properly.
而且它确实为我详细说明了 未终止的字符串文字
And it does elaborate for me, unterminated string literal.
现在 这有点神秘
Now, that's a bit arcane.
这是一个有点令人困惑的错误消息
That is a bit of a confusing error message.
但未终止通常意味着我
But unterminated would generally mean that I
引发了一些事情 但并没有阻止它
started something but didn't stop it.
我没有终止它
I didn't terminate it.
当然 字符串是一个文本序列 就像我们之前讨论过的那样--
String, of course, is a sequence of text, like we've discussed before--
或者在Python中搅拌
or stir in Python.
而字面意思通常是指你按字面意思打字的东西
And literal generally refers to something that you literally typed.
它不是一个变量
It's not a variable.
这就像是引号--
It's something like quote unquote--
或者只说“你好 世界
or just "hello world.
所以 这里的解决办法当然是
So the fix here, of course, is going to be
继续并终止该字符串 并实际结束引号
to go ahead and terminate that string and actually close the quote.
如果我现在回到我的终端窗口
And if I now go back down into my terminal window
重新运行hello.py的Python 现在我要向世界问好了
and rerun Python of hello.py, now I'm saying hello to the world.
因此 这里语法错误的问题是 语法错误完全是
So the catch with syntax errors here is that syntax errors are entirely
由你来解决
on you to solve.
语法错误是一个问题 您必须返回到代码中
A syntax error is a problem that you've got to go back into your code
从一开始就解决问题
and fix from the get-go.
你不能只希望它会
You can't just kind of hope that it's going
来自行解决 或者期望代码的其他部分
to resolve itself or expect that other parts of your code
会帮你抓到的
will catch it for you.
语法错误只是必须被修复
Syntax errors just must be fixed.
但是在Python中还有很多其他类型的错误
But there's a lot of other types of errors in Python
这可能被描述为运行时错误
that might be described as runtime errors, that
在代码运行时发生
happen while your code is running.
这真的是由您来编写一些额外的防御性代码
And it's really up to you to write some additional code defensively
来检测这些错误何时发生 因为你不一定知道
to detect when those errors happen because you don't necessarily know,
例如 人类将在您的程序中输入什么输入
for instance, what input humans are going to type into your program.
所以你最好做好准备 防御性的 去适应
And so you better be ready, defensively, to accommodate things
他们打字 甚至打错字
that they type or even misstype.
所以 举个例子 让我们回到VS代码
So, for instance, let's go back over here to VS Code.
让我提议我们一起来看一份新文件
And let me propose that we take a look at a new file all together.
我将关闭hello.py
I'm going to close hello.py.
我要写一段代码 比如number.py
And I'm going to write code of say number.py.
因此 让我们在Python语言中使用一些数字
So let's play around with some numbers in Python.
我要在这里做的第一件事是使用number.py
And the first thing I'm going to go ahead here and do with number.py,
在打开这个新标签后 我想我要继续打印--
after opening this new tab, is I think I'm going to go ahead and print--
输入一个相对简单的程序 该程序可能会提示用户输入一个整数
type up a relatively simple program that maybe prompts the user for an integer,
比如x 然后打印出x是什么
like x, and then just prints out what x is.
所以我们将从简单开始 但是 再次 从简单开始
So we're going to start simple, but, again, in starting simple,
我们将能够真正看到我做错了什么
we'll be able to really see where I've done something wrong.
好了 我们开始吧
Well, here we go.
我接下来要说的是一个名为
I'm going to go ahead and say a variable called
X将被赋值为输入的返回值
x is going to get assigned the value of the return value of input,
引述：“什么是x？”
quote unquote, "what's x?"
我将包括一个空间 用于将光标移动到上方一点
And I'm going to include a space to move the cursor over a little bit.
然后 最终 我要继续--哦 等一下
And then, ultimately, I'm going to go ahead and-- oh, wait a minute.
如果我想从用户那里获得一个int
If I'm wanting to get an int from the user,
回想一下 我需要主动做一些事情
recall that I need to do something proactively.
我需要使用以下命令将该输入实际转换为整数
I need to actually convert that input to an integer using
Python中的int函数
the int function in Python.
所以现在我将输入的返回值作为参数传递给int
So now I'm passing the return value of input as the argument to int.
最终 它将在x中存储一个整数 而不是
And that will store in x, ultimately, an integer, not
看起来像整数的字符串
a string that looks like an integer.
好了 现在让我继续 只是简单地打印出这是什么
All right, let me go ahead now and just quite simply print out what this is.
我将继续打印出来 引用引号 “x就是x ”
I'm going to go ahead and print out, quote unquote, "x is x."
但我不想从字面上说x就是x
But I don't want to literally say x is x.
我想插入x的值
I want to plug in the value of x.
因此 也许最简单的方法是用花括号将其括起来
So maybe the easiest way to do that is to surround it with curly braces.
然后如果我用这些花括号 我
And then if I'm using these curly braces and I
我想让Python对该变量的值进行内插
want Python to interpolate the value of that variable,
这就是用x在这些花括号之间的实际位置替换
that is substitute what x actually is in between those curly braces,
回想一下 我需要使用格式字符串或F字符串
recall that I need to use a format string or an F-string
通过用F来解决这整件事 现在我已经做到了 让我们继续
by fixing this whole thing with an F. Now that I've done that, let's go ahead
看看会发生什么
and see what happens.
我将在我的终端窗口中继续运行Numer.py的Python
I'm going to go ahead in my terminal window and run Python of number.py.
我按了Enter键
I hit Enter.
到目前为止 一切都很好
And so far, so good.
一切都很好 并被提示输入x
All is well and being prompted for x.
让我继续输入一个数字 比如50
Let me go ahead and type in a number like 50.
好的 这似乎起作用了
All right, that seems to work.
程序似乎是正确的
Program seems to be correct.
还是真的是这样？
Or is it?
这个程序可能会出什么问题 即使没有出现任何错误？
What could go wrong in this program, even though nothing did just go wrong?
但如果我运行它 运行它 再运行它
But if I run it and run it and run it again,
在我的程序运行过程中 还可能出现什么问题
during the running of my program, what could still go wrong,
尤其是如果我不是和它互动的人
especially if I'm not the human interacting with it
而是另一个人类呢？
but some other human instead?
这里有志愿者参加这个活动吗？
Any volunteers here for this one?
会出什么问题呢？
What could go wrong?
这个程序在什么方面不是真正正确的 甚至
And in what way is this program not really correct, even
尽管乍一看似乎是这样
though at first glance it seems so.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
大卫·马兰：所以我不会叫一个整数
DAVID MALAN: So I'm not calling an integer.
我还是听不清你的话
I'm still having trouble hearing you.
但我想我听到的是 如果用户输入的内容不是
But what I think I heard is that if what the user types in is not,
事实上 一个整数 我不能盲目地把它转换成一个整型
in fact, an integer, I can't just blindly convert it to an int.
如果我没把太多话塞进你嘴里
If I'm not putting too many words into your mouth,
我想我在这里可能应该做的是有点防御性
I think what I should perhaps do here is be a little defensive.
让我看看我是否不能准确地模拟这个问题
And let me see if I can't simulate exactly the problem that
可能会出问题
could go wrong here.
让我继续运行 再一次 数字.py的Python
Let me go ahead and run, again, Python of number.py.
让我试试另一个号码
Let me try another number.
事实上 在测试代码时 通常
In fact, when testing your code, generally it's
测试角点情况是个好主意 也许数字不是那么简单
a good idea to test corner cases, maybe numbers that aren't quite as plain as
或者49或51岁
or 49 or 51.
让我们选择一些可能更有趣的数字 如果
Let's choose some numbers that might be a little more interesting, if only
从数学上讲 就像是零
mathematically, like zero.
好的 零利率似乎起作用了
All right, zero seems to work.
我的代码仍然打印出x为零
My code still prints out that x is zero.
另一个需要考虑的角落案例可能是什么？
What might be another corner case to consider?
好吧 让我继续尝试一个负数
Well, let me go ahead and try a negative number.
这在精神上也与消极的截然不同
That, too, is pretty different in spirit from negative.
负1？
Negative 1?
好的 这也行
OK, that works too.
好吧 让我再试一次
Well, let me try it one more time.
我试过正数 负数 0
I've tried positive numbers, negative numbers, 0.
让我试试像猫一样的东西
Let me try something like a cat.
所以从字面上讲 C-A-T--输入一个看起来甚至不像数字的字符串
So literally, C-A-T-- typing in a string that doesn't even look like a number.
不过 现在让我们看看当我按Enter键时会发生什么
And yet, let's see now what happens when I hit Enter.
好的 现在我们来看看我们有另一种错误
All right, we'll see now we've got another kind of error.
这不是语法错误 因为我没有犯打字错误
It's not a syntax error, because I didn't make a typographical mistake.
我没有忘记一些语法
I didn't forget some piece of syntax.
实际上 现在我的一个值出现了错误
I actually now have an error with one of my values.
这是一个我甚至都没有预料到的价值
And it's an a value I didn't even anticipate.
在这种情况下 这个人 也就是我 在我写代码很久之后才输入了它
The human, me, in this case typed it in long after I wrote the code.
那么这指的是什么呢？
So what does this refer to?
值错误
A value error.
好吧 让我们看看是什么解释
Well, let's see what the explanation is.
基数为10的int的文本无效 请不要用引号引“cat”
Invalid literal for int with base 10, quote unquote, "cat."
现在 这也是一个有点冗长的问题
Now, this, too, is a bit of a mouthful.
不幸的是 在Python语言和许多编程语言中
And, unfortunately, in Python and a lot of programming languages,
这些错误消息是为非常舒适的程序员编写的
the error messages are written for pretty comfortable programmers.
当然 当你第一次学习编程时
And, of course, when you're learning programming for the first time,
您可能对编程语言不是很熟悉
you might not be so comfortable with the programming language
更不用说错误消息了
let alone the error messages.
但让我们看看我们是否能收集到一些洞察力
But let's see if we can't glean some insight.
所以是无效的文字
So invalid literal.
好吧 再说一次 文字只是输入的东西 看起来
Well, again, a literal is just something that's been typed in, it would seem,
用于INT
for int.
Int到底是什么？
What is int exactly?
好的 int是我用来转换用户的
Well, int is the function I'm using to convert the user's
输入到相应的整数
input to a corresponding integer.
以10为基数 指的是十进制 即
Base 10, that refers to the decimal system, which is this
这是Python使用的默认设置
the default that Python is using.
归根结底 它看起来就像是 Python真正
And it looks like at the end of the day, what Python really
我不喜欢的是 我把cat传递给了int函数
doesn't like is that I passed cat, quote unquote, "to the int function."
那么 我该如何着手实际解决这个问题呢？
So how do I go about actually fixing this problem?
嗯 我可以在我的程序中添加指令
Well, I could just add instructions in my program.
或许我可以加一行文字告诉你
Maybe I could add a line of print telling
用户更明确地说 一定要键入一个整数
the user more explicitly, be sure to type an integer,
或者 请不要输入cat
or, please don't type cat.
请不要键入字符串
Please don't type strings.
当然 用户可能仍然不会满足要求
Of course, the user might still not oblige.
他们可能没有读到说明书
They might not be reading the instruction.
因此 这也可能不是一个有效的策略
So that too is probably not an effective strategy.
我们真正想要做的是在编写代码时考虑到错误处理
What we really want to do is write our code with error handling in mind.
我们想要编写的代码行不仅能实现
We want to write lines of code that not only accomplish
我们关心的问题 但这也解决了
the problems we care about but that also handle
可能意外发生的错误
errors that might unexpectedly happen.
而且 一般来说 当编程时 编程是防御性的
And, in general, when programming, programming defensively.
假设用户不会注意 或者 更糟糕的是
Assume that the users aren't going to be paying attention or, worse,
他们很恶毒
they're malicious.
他们想让你的程序崩溃
They're trying to crash your program.
因此 我们希望尽可能多地处理错误
So we want to handle as many errors as we can.
现在 我们如何在Python中做到这一点呢？
Now, how do we go about doing that in Python?
好的 结果是您想要捕获值错误还是其他类型
Well, it turns out whether you want to catch a value error or other types
也有错误--尽管不是语法错误--
of errors as well-- though not syntax error--
Python实际上有一个名为try的关键字
Python actually has this keyword called try.
它的名字有点贴切
And it's sort of aptly named.
如果您想尝试用Python语言做一些事情
If you want to try to do something in Python,
你可以从字面上使用这个关键字
you can literally use this keyword.
你可以检查是否有一些特殊的东西 一些
And you can check whether or not something exceptional, something
错误 已经发生了
erroneous, has happened.
所以同时使用try和这个关键字 除了
So using both try and this other keyword, except,
除非出了什么差错 否则我能去试着做点什么吗？
can I go and try to do something except if something goes wrong?
我可以做些别的事来代替
I can do something else instead.
所以让我们想想 我怎么才能开始尝试
So let's consider, how can I go about trying
除非出现错误 否则是否将用户的输入转换为int？
to convert the user's input to an int except if something goes wrong?
好吧 让我回到我的代码这里
Well, let me go back to my code here.
让我提议我现在修改这个例子如下
And let me propose that I now modify this example as follows.
让我继续 在我的第一行代码之上
Let me go ahead and, above my first line of code,
我真的写了 试着加了一个冒号 告诉Python
I literally write, try and a colon, telling Python,
尝试执行以下操作
try to do the following.
我将继续并缩进我现有的代码行
I'm going to go ahead and indent my existing lines of codes
这里有相同数量的空格 在这种情况下是四个
here by the same number of spaces, four in this case.
然后我要在这里再加一行 字面意思是
And then I'm going to add one more new line down here that literally says,
值错误除外
except Value Error.
请注意 重要的是我将V大写
And notice it's important that I've capitalized the V
我把E大写了 这些符号区分大小写
and I've capitalized the E. These symbols are case sensitive.
现在这是一个机会 在这个冒号之后
And this is now an opportunity, after this colon,
告诉Python我想在异常情况下做什么 当
to tell Python what I want to do in exceptional cases, when
事实上 数字或来自用户的输入不是数字
the number or the input from the user is not, in fact, a number.
我会说一些简单的东西 比如印刷品 引用引号
And I'm going to say something plain like print, quote unquote,
“x不是整数 ”
"x is not an integer."
我至少会粗略地告诉用户问题到底是什么
I'm at least going to tell the user roughly what the problem actually is.
所以请注意另一个细节
So notice another detail.
压痕很重要
The indentation is important.
因为我试了一下第一行 我缩进了第二行和第三行 那些
Because I have try on line one and I've indented lines two and three, those
是我正在尝试的两行代码 除非我看到值错误
are the two lines of code that I'm trying, except if I see a value error,
第五行 因为它是缩进的
line five, because it's indented is what is
在这些错误的情况下会被处决
going to get executed in cases of those errors.
现在让我继续返回到我的终端窗口 并运行number.py的Python
Let me go ahead now back to my terminal window and run Python of number.py,
进来吧
Enter.
让我们继续 再输入一次
And let's go ahead and type in again.
看起来还是有效的
Still seems to work.
当然 我正在努力 并取得了成功
And, of course, I'm trying and succeeding.
不过 让我再试一次 这次用猫这个词
Let me go ahead and try once more, this time, though, with the word cat
或者 真的 任何不是十进制数的东西
or, really, anything that's not a decimal number.
现在你们会更清楚地看到 x不是整数
And now you'll see much more cleanly x is not an integer.
我没有看到一些可怕的错误消息
I'm not seeing some scary error message that I, the user,
我不知道该怎么处理
am going to have no idea how to handle.
现在你 程序员 已经预料到
Now you, the programmer, have anticipated
一些特殊的事情可能会发生
that something exceptional can happen.
您已经开始为用户实际处理错误
And you've gone about actually handling the error for the user,
而是向他们提供适当的错误消息
giving them an appropriate error message instead.
让我在这里停一停 看看 现在还有什么问题吗
Let me pause here and see, are there any questions now
关于我们刚刚通过引入Try所做的事情
on what we've just done by introducing try
并接受处理此值错误吗？
and accept to handle this value error?
观众：价值是你唯一能得到的错误类型吗？
AUDIENCE: Is value ever the only type of error you can get?
或者还有其他类型的吗？
Or are there other types?
大卫·马兰：值错误是你唯一能抓到的东西吗？
DAVID MALAN: Is value error the only thing you can catch?
还有其他错误
There are other errors as well.
今天我们将看到其中的几个
And we'll see a few of them today.
老实说 如果你继续这样做 还有很多很多
And there's many, many more, honestly, that if you continue
使用Python进行编程和编程 您将
programming and programming in Python, you're
在接下来的几周、几个月、几年里 我们会看到很多这样的动物
going to see a lot of them over the weeks the months the years to come.
但处理它们的技术正在走向
But the technique for handling them is going
在尝试、接受、
to be largely the same other questions on try, accept,
或者更笼统地说 这些例外？
or these exceptions more generally?
观众：是的 先生
AUDIENCE: Yes, sir.
实际上 要使用Except块 您需要知道错误的类型 对吗？
Actually, to use the except block, you need to know the type of error, right?
[听不见]如果你无法预料到这种特殊类型的错误 该怎么办？
[INAUDIBLE] what if you can't anticipate this particular type of error?
大卫·马兰：这是一个非常好的问题
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
所以我非常擅长捕捉 可以这么说
So I'm being very good about catching, so to speak,
我可能会犯的错误
the very error that I might happen.
我不知道什么时候会发生 因为它是
I don't know when it might happen because it's
这将取决于用户
going to depend on the user.
但我知道int函数会出现什么样的错误
But I know what kind of error will happen from the int function.
在Python中有一种方法可以说 除非出现任何错误
There is a way in Python where you can say, except if anything goes wrong.
您完全可以省略值错误 只需捕获所有内容
And you can literally omit value error and just catch everything.
这样做的问题是 它有时会在代码中隐藏其他错误
The problem with that is that it sometimes hides other bugs in your code
因为你不一定知道哪里出了问题
because you don't necessarily know what's going wrong.
如果你不一定知道哪里出了问题
And if you don't necessarily know what's going wrong,
你怎么可能正确地处理它呢？
how can you possibly handle it correctly?
太糟糕的练习了
So bad practice.
换句话说 这样做是懒惰的 只是说 捕捉一切
And it put another way, it's lazy to do that, to just say, catch everything
我会在这里处理的
and I'll deal with it here.
因此 更好的做法是找出哪种错误
So a much better practice would be to figure out what kind of errors
可能会发生 并包括明确提到它们 就像我所做的那样
could happen and include mention of them explicitly, as I have done.
话虽如此 如果您阅读了Python的官方文档
Now, with that said, if you read Python's official documentation,
就像你最终都会做的那样 它不是
as you'll eventually invariably do, it is not
非常乐意主动告诉您哪些类型的错误
great about telling you proactively what kinds of errors
都可以这样养大
can be raised in this way.
因此 这是一个自相矛盾的建议
So it's a bit of contradictory advice.
你该这么做
You should do it this way.
但是 你应该检查什么并不总是显而易见的
But it's not always obvious what you should be checking for.
但通过练习 你会做得更好
But you get better at it with practice.
在某些情况下 文档确实会详细说明可能出现的问题
And some of the times, the documentation does spell out what could go wrong.
现在让我把注意力转回到这个问题上
Let me turn our attention now back to this
并指出 即使这是更好的代码
and point out that even though this is better code,
它更正确的意义在于 我不只是把它留给用户
it is more correct in the sense that I'm not just leaving it to the user
要查看大多数人都会看到的非常难看的默认Python错误消息
to see some really ugly default Python error message that most people are
我不知道该怎么做 我
going to have no idea what to do with, I'm
至少要更优雅地处理它
at least handling it more elegantly.
我打印出来的x不是整数
And I'm printing out x is not an integer.
因此 它至少更有教育意义
So it's at least more instructive.
但这不一定是实现此代码的最佳方式
But this isn't necessarily the best way to implement this code.
为什么？
Why?
好吧 在这里 我实际上还是有点懒
Well, here, too, I'm actually still being a little lazy.
请注意 我正在尝试编写的不是一行代码 而是两行代码
So notice that I'm trying to do not one line of code but two lines of code.
这不是什么大事 因为我们只讨论了两行代码
And this isn't a huge deal because we're only talking about two lines of code.
但为了宣扬最佳实践
But in the interest of preaching best practices,
您真的应该只尝试执行一行或很少的代码
you should really only be trying to do the one or very few lines of code that
实际上可能会引发异常 但实际上可能会以某种方式失败
can actually raise an exception that can actually fail in some way.
我非常确定在这里调用print不会引发值错误
I am pretty sure that calling print here is not going to raise a value error.
无论x是整型、字符串、浮点型还是其他任何类型
Whether x is an int or a string or a float or anything else,
Python的格式字符串功能将很好地处理打印
the format string feature of Python is going to handle printing it just fine.
所以 真的 我要做的是这样的
So, really, what I'm going to do is this.
我将把这第三行移到代码的底部
I'm going to move this line three down to the bottom of my code.
我不再需要缩进它
I no longer need to indent it.
我将在我的文件的底部执行它
I'm just going to execute it at the bottom of my file here.
不幸的是 通过这样做--
Unfortunately, by doing this--
到目前为止 我已经做了一件好事 只是试着做最少的工作
I've done a good thing by now only trying to do the minimal amount of work
这可能会引发值错误的异常
necessary that might raise the exception of value error.
但我恐怕我引入了一个新的错误
But I fear I've introduced a new mistake.
好吧 让我想想
Well, let's see.
现在什么是不正确的？
What is now incorrect?
让我继续并再次运行number.py的Python 回车
Let me go ahead and again run Python of number.py, Enter.
让我继续下去 正确地做50
Let me go ahead and do it correctly with 50.
一切似乎都很顺利
And all seems to be well.
但是 再一次 让我们来看看那些角落里的案例--
But, again, let's try those corner cases--
零 负数 或者 在这种情况下 是猫
the zeros, the negative numbers, or, in this case, the cat.
让我继续输入C-A-T
Let me go ahead and type in C-A-T again.
进来吧
Enter.
现在我有一个名字错误
Now I have a name error.
所以现在我在这里介绍的代码中还有另一种类型的错误
So now it's yet another type of error in my code that I've introduced here.
这个名字错误是什么意思？
And what does this name error mean?
正如值误差所指的那样--某个变量的值
Well, just as a value error refers to that-- the value of some variable,
有人输入的值不正确--
the value that someone has typed in is incorrect--
名称错误倾向于引用您的代码 就像您正在使用
name error tends to refer to your code, like you're doing something with
不应该使用的变量的名称
the name of a variable that you shouldn't.
为什么会这样呢？
And why might that be?
好了 让我们把注意力转回到代码上
Well, let me turn our attention back to the code
这里想一想 它在抱怨什么？
here and consider, what is it complaining about?
好吧 这个名字和我在这里看到的是不一样的
Well, the name errors what I see down here.
它告诉我 名字 引号 “x是没有定义的 “
And it's telling me, name, quote unquote, "x is not defined."
注意 如果我看得更远 它提到了第六行
And notice if I look further here, it is mentioning line six.
所以我知道问题出在第六行的代码上
So I know the problem is with my code on line six.
刚才还奏效了
And that worked a moment ago.
我在第二行定义x
And I'm defining x on line two.
但让我问一下这里的小组 为什么x 实际上 存在于在线6？
But let me ask the group here, why does x, in fact, exist online six?
为什么它没有定义 即使我很确定我
Why is it not defined, even though I'm pretty sure I
打算在第二行定义它吗
was intending to define it on line two?
或许 这是一种“不为人知”的行为
AUDIENCE: Maybe the scope of the variable is between the [INAUDIBLE]..
大卫·马兰：好的术语
DAVID MALAN: So, good terminology.
作用域是指变量所在的代码部分
Scope refers to the portion of code in which a variable exists.
这在Python中也不太正确
That, too, though isn't quite right in Python.
这在C、C++和Java中是正确的 缩进或花括号往往
That would be true in C, C++, and Java, where indentation or curly braces tend
定义变量的作用域
to define the scope of a variable.
但是 一般来说
But, again, here in general--
刚才还管用
and this worked a moment ago.
X在第二行定义后就存在了 因为 记住
X exists once it's defined on line two because, remember,
我之前打印了x是50
I printed out x is 50 a little bit ago.
让我们再做一个假设
Let's try one more hypothesis here.
再来一把？
One more hand?
为什么x还没有被定义？
Why is x somehow still not defined?
观众：是的 因为它是局部变量
AUDIENCE: Yeah, so is it because it's local variable,
这意味着它不会定义范围之外的
meaning that it doesn't define outside of the scope
因为人们提到的
because what people have mentioned.
它提示try中的输入 对吗？
It prompts the input in try, right?
它的外部是不确定的
The outside of it is undefined.
DAVID MALAN：所以还是很好的直觉
DAVID MALAN: So still good instincts.
好的术语 也是
And good terminology, too.
有一个局部变量的概念 它往往存在于
There's this notion of local variables, which tend to exist inside
函数 例如 全局变量
of functions, for instance, global variables,
它们往往存在于整个文件中
which tend to exist in entire files.
不过 在这个例子中 情况也并非如此
In this case, too, though, that's not quite the case.
这里发生的事情归结为操作顺序
What's happening here boils down to order of operations.
让我回到代码中 回想一下
Let me come back to the code here and recall that any time we've
讨论了赋值运算符 即单个等号
discussed the assignment operator, the single equal sign, that copies
从右到左的值
a value from the right to the left.
但是 请考虑一下 在什么情况下会出现问题
But consider for a moment at what point something is going wrong.
输入功能可能工作正常
Well, the input function is probably working just fine
因为我们现在已经经常使用它来获取用户的输入
because we've used that a lot now to get users' input.
它总是在Python中返回一个字符串或搅拌器
It always returns a string or a stir in Python.
但会出什么问题呢？
But what could be going wrong?
如果我将该字符串作为参数传递给int函数
Well, if I'm passing that string to the int function as its argument,
可能是int的函数出错了
it's probably the int's function that's erroring.
事实上 如果你回想一下之前当我们有值错误的时候
And, indeed, if you think back earlier when we had the value error,
事实上 它是int函数 它没有
it was, in fact, the int function that did not
比如 不加引号的“猫”作为输入
like, quote unquote, "cat" as input.
所以这就是说 我的这部分代码
So this is all to say that this portion of my code
现在突出显示在等号右侧 即
highlighted now to the right of the equal sign, that's
造成问题的代码
the code that's creating a problem.
这就是产生值错误的代码
That's the code that was creating a value error.
在这种情况下 我们捕捉到了值错误
And in this case, we're catching the value error.
但是因为值错误发生在等号的右侧
But because the value error is happening on the right of the equal sign,
向左复制没有任何价值
there's no value being copied to the left.
这个错误正在中断整个过程
The error is interrupting that whole process.
所以即使我们在第二行看到x等于点
So even though we see x equals dot dot dot on line two,
等号左边那行的那部分
the portion of that line to the left of the equal sign
最终不会被评估 因为价值
isn't getting evaluated, ultimately, because the value
错误发生得太快了
error is happening too soon.
因此 当我们最终到达第六行时
And so when we finally get down to line six,
尽管这看起来像是我在第二条线上定义--
even though it looked like I was defining on line two--
如果一切顺利 我会在第二行定义x--
and I would have defined x on line two if all had gone well--
我们没有到达从右到左复制值的部分
we didn't get to the part where the value is copied from right to left
因为值错误最先发生
because the value error happened first.
所以这个代码现在是不正确的
So this code is just incorrect now.
那么 我该如何着手解决这样的问题呢？
So how do I go about solving something like this?
嗯 事实证明 这一尝试还有另一个特点
Well, it turns out that there's another feature of the try
并接受Python支持的语法 即
and accept syntax that Python supports, which is
它还支持关键字Else
that it also supports the keyword else.
现在 我们以前见过其他的情况
Now, we've seen else before.
如果你回想一下我们对条件句的讨论 我们看到了if
If you think back to our discussion of conditionals, we saw if.
我们看到了埃利夫
We saw elif.
我们看到了其他的 这是一种笼统的 什么
We saw else, which was kind of this catchall, what
你应该在其他事情都不相关的情况下这样做
you should do in the event that nothing else is relevant.
在这里 除了Python的Try-Expect特性之外 这是一种相同的直觉
That's kind of the same intuition here for the try-except feature of Python.
你能做的就是这样
What you can do is this.
您可以尝试执行以下操作 就像我所做的那样 除非出现错误
You can try to do the following, as I've done, except if this goes wrong.
但如果没出什么差错 那就这么做吧
But if nothing goes wrong, else go ahead and do this.
所以这是我现在可以解决同样问题的一种方法
So this is one way I can solve this same problem now.
无论现在是什么情况 Python都会尝试执行第二行
No matter what now, Python is going to try to execute line two.
如果出现错误 它将执行第三行
If something goes wrong, it's going to execute lines three
四个用于处理该值错误
and four to handle that value error.
但是 如果您尝试了 并且此代码成功了
However, if you try and this code succeeds,
那么就不会有例外需要处理
then there is no exception to handle.
所以你要在这里执行这一行
So you're then going to execute this line here.
所以 这可能有点令人困惑
So it's a little confusing, perhaps, in that
我们现在把两者都用在条件句中--if Elif Elif Elif
we're now using else both for conditionals-- if, elif, elif, elif,
不然的话
else.
我们还对这些try-Expect块使用了Else
And we're also using else with these try-except blocks.
但那也没关系
But that's OK.
这是语言的一部分
That's part of the language.
这是其中一个特点
That's one of the features.
现在 如果我在我的终端窗口中重新运行这段代码 即number.py的Python--
So now if I rerun this code in my terminal window, Python of number.py--
让我们做一些正确的事情 比如50--
let's do something correct, like 50--
我知道x是50
I see that x is 50.
所以第一行被执行了
So line one is executed.
我们正在努力做到以下几点
We're trying to do the following.
执行第二行是因为转换成功
Line two is executed because the conversion happened successfully
数字50从右到左复制
and the number 50 gets copied from right to left.
这种例外情况不会发生
The exception does not happen.
所以我们忽略了第三行和第四行
So we ignore lines three and four.
我们立即跳到第五行和第六行 打印出结果
We jump immediately to line five and six, which prints out the result.
相比之下 让我们最后一次来做这件事
By contrast, though-- let's do this one last time.
PY.--让我们输入cat或任何其他单词 然后按Enter键
Python of number.py-- let's type in cat or, again, any other word and hit Enter
现在
now.
我们看不到x是什么
We don't see what x is.
相反 我们看到 不加引号 “x不是一个整数 ”
Rather, we see, quote unquote, "x is not an integer,"
这就是我的例外条款所处理的问题
which is what's being handled in my except clause.
好了 让我暂停一下 因为这有很多新的语法
All right, let me pause here because that's a lot of new syntax,
看看这里是否有任何关于尝试的问题 除了
and see here if there's any questions on try, on except,
On Else、名称错误或值错误
on else, name error, or value error.
观众：请重复一下Try功能好吗？
AUDIENCE: Can you please repeat the try function?
大卫·马兰：重复这个名字错误？
DAVID MALAN: Repeat the name error?
名字错误有什么问题？
What's the problem with the name error?
观众：是的
AUDIENCE: Yes.
是
Yes.
大卫·马兰：是的
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
所以让我们倒回几句台词
So let's just rewind a couple of lines here
在我解决这个问题之前 现在把其他的都处理掉
before I fix this problem by now getting rid of the else.
刚才 我们有这样的代码 其中
A moment ago, we had code that looked like this, whereby
我收到了一个名称错误 PYTHON of Numer.py Enter
I was getting a name error, Python of number.py, Enter,
输入cat 结果如下所示 其中没有定义名称x
typing in cat, that looked like this, where name x is not defined.
根据这段用Python语言编写的输出 问题出现在第六行
And the problem was on line six, according to this output in Python.
好 现在让我们演绎地考虑一下
Well, let's think about this now deductively.
让我们尝试一种不同的方法
Let's try a different approach.
在第六行 我看到一个错误 没有定义名称x
On line six, I'm seeing an error that name x is not defined.
好吧 在这一点上 Python已经告诉我x并不存在
OK, Python's already telling me x does not exist at that point.
那么这怎么可能呢？
So how could that possibly be?
那么 x应该在哪里定义呢？
Well, where should x be defined?
很可能 x的定义在第二行 在这里
Well, presumably, x is defined on line two, up here.
那么 可能会出什么问题呢？
So what could go wrong?
嗯 如果用户输入了看起来不像数字的东西
Well, if the user has inputted something that doesn't look like a number,
就像单词猫 传递猫 输入的返回值
like the word cat, passing cat, the return value of input,
因为将单词转换为int的int参数没有任何意义
as the argument to int to convert the word to an int makes no sense.
您根本不能将CAT C-A-T转换为整数
You can't convert a cat, C-A-T, to an integer at all.
因此 int函数在该点引发了一个值错误
So the int function is raising a value error at that point.
这个错误是用这个代码来处理的
And the error is being handled with this code here.
但请注意 这第六行没有缩进
But notice this line six is not indented.
它与我的其余代码左对齐 这意味着无论发生什么
It's left aligned with the rest of my code, which means no matter what,
第六行将执行
line six is going to execute.
无论我输入的是50还是CAT 它都会执行
It's going to execute whether I typed in 50 or I typed in cat.
但如果我再一次输入cat x永远不会得到值
But if I typed in cat, again, x never gets a value.
所以它没有在这里的第六行定义
So it's not defined here on line six.
所以 当我最后介绍Else语句时
So when I introduced, finally, the else statement, that
确保这些东西是相互排斥的
makes sure that these things are mutually exclusive.
只有当我在上面尝试并成功时 我才会执行Else
I only execute the else if I tried and succeeded up above.
好吧 让我建议我们再进一步改进一下
Well, let me propose that we refine this just a little bit further as well
并考虑如何进一步改进此示例
and consider how we might improve this example a little bit more.
我拒绝用户的输入是有点不友好 因为他们
It's a little unfriendly of me to be rejecting the user's input after they
没有提供一个整数 就直接退出程序 真的吗？
fail to provide an integer and just quitting the program, really, right?
如果我只提示用户 它会更友好
It'd be more user friendly if I just prompt
或一次又一次地重新提示用户
or reprompt the user again and again.
在聊天中 如果可以的话 Python的功能是什么
And in the chat, if you could, what's the feature of Python
如果你想一次又一次地做某事 你可以使用它
that you can use if you want to do something again and again
直到用户与您合作并为您提供
and again until such time as the user cooperates and gives you
你在找什么 比如一个数字？
what you're looking for, like a number?
所以 是的 循环
So yeah, loop, loop, loop.
所以循环就是一次又一次发生的事情
So a loop is something that happens again and again and again.
也许我们可以使用同样的机制 循环 按顺序
And maybe we can use that same mechanism, a loop, in order
以提示用户输入x
to prompt the user for x.
如果他们不给我们一个数字 再次提示他们
And if they don't give us a number, prompt them again.
如果他们没有 就一次又一次地提示他们
And if they don't, prompt them again and again and again.
我们不需要就这么退出这个项目
We don't need to just quit out of the program.
所以 快点--所以让我提出这个建议
So, quickly-- so let me propose this.
让我在这里建议我通过故意这样做来改进这段代码
Let me propose here that I improve this code by deliberately doing this.
让我用While True在代码的最顶端引入一个无限循环
Let me induce a infinite loop at the very top of my code with while true.
回想一下 Wild关键字引发了一个循环 循环的行为如下所示
Recall that the wild keyword induces a loop, a cycle that behaves like this.
它会问一个问题 一个布尔表达式
And it asks a question, a Boolean expression
这需要计算为真或假
that needs to evaluate either to true or false.
好吧 如果我想让这个东西永远循环
Well, if I want this thing to loop forever,
至少在一开始 我们只会说虽然为真 因为真就是真
at least initially, we'll just say while true because true is true.
所以这有做一些事情的效果
So this has the effect of doing something
不管发生什么 除非我们早点挣脱
no matter what forever unless we break out of it early.
现在我要继续做这件事
Now I'm going to go ahead and do this.
我将继续移动我的Try 除了代码
I'm going to go ahead and move my try except code
在这个循环下面缩进 所以我试着得到一个x
indented underneath this loop so that I'm trying to get an x.
如果我有一个值错误 我会打印出x不是一个整数
If I have a value error instead, I print out x is not an integer.
但这一次 如果用户这样做了 我想做什么呢
But this time, what do I want to do if the user does
试着成功地给我一个号码？
try and succeed in giving me a number?
好吧 我能做到的
Well, I can do this.
我可以在这里突破我的密码
I can just break out of my code here.
现在在这里 我可以使用相同的代码行
And down here now, I can use that same line of code
从前面开始 一个F字符串表示x是 然后在花括号中 又是x
from before, an F-string that says x is, and then in curly braces, x again.
这是怎么回事？
So what's going on here?
我现在认为这个代码 因为我已经添加了
I think this code now, because I've added
循环 将产生至少尝试一次的效果 也许
the loop, is going to have the effect of trying at least once, maybe
第二次 也许第三次 可能是500次 直到用户最终给出
a second time, maybe a third time maybe 500 times until the user finally gives
告诉我我想要什么 这是一个整数
me what I want, which is an integer.
一旦他们这样做了 一旦没有值错误发生
And once they do, once there's no value error happening,
然后我就跳出了圈子
then I break out of the loop.
正如我所希望的那样 执行第九行
And line nine executes as I would hope.
所以让我继续试着执行这个版本--
So let me go ahead and try executing this version--
Paython.py 回车
Python of number.py, Enter.
X是什么？
What's x?
让我先把最简单的东西打进去--
Let me go ahead and type in the easy thing first--
50美元
50.
X等于50
X is 50.
就控制流而言 刚刚发生了什么
What just happened in terms of the control flow
这个节目 我的逻辑是什么？
of this program, the flow of my logic?
嗯 我首先发现自己在一个环路内的一号线上
Well, I first found myself on line one inside of a loop.
希望我能走出这个循环
Hopefully, I'll get out of this loop.
然后我做了什么？
What did I then do?
在第二行和第三行 我尝试从用户那里获得输入
On lines two and three, I tried to get input from the user
并将其转换为整型
and convert it to an int.
好吧 这次我是个好人
Well, I was a nice guy this time.
然后我输入了50 它看起来像是一个数字
And I typed in 50, which looks like and is a number.
因此 int函数将其转换得很好
So the int function converted it just fine
并将其从右到左存储在x中
and stored it from right to left in x.
除数值错误外？
Except value error?
没有值错误 因为如果我输入一个数字
There is no value error because if I typed in a number,
没有什么特别的事情发生
there's nothing exceptional happening.
这是一个无聊的 很好的执行我的程序
This is a boring, good execution of my program.
那么会发生什么呢？
So what happens?
我跳出了圈子
I break out of the loop.
因此 Else子句再一次与try NOT和EXCEPT关联
So, again, the else clause is associated with the try not with the except.
一旦我退出循环 当然 我只是打印出x是什么
And once I'm out of the loop, of course, I'm just printing out what x is.
好吧 让我们来看看另一种可能发生的情况
Well, let's try the other scenario that might happen.
Paython.py 回车
Python of number.py, Enter.
X是什么？
What's x?
让我们试试猫或其他任何词
Let's try cat or any other word.
进来吧
Enter.
啊 这是现在的一个新功能
Ah, this is now a new feature.
我被告知我做错了什么
I'm being informed what I did wrong.
X不是整数
X is not an integer.
所以我得到了一些有用的用户反馈
So I'm getting some useful user feedback.
但请注意 再次提示我 x是什么？
But notice, again, I'm prompted, what's x?
好的 让我试着输入“狗”
Well, let me try typing in dog.
X不是整数
X is not an integer.
X是什么？
What's x?
让我试试伯德
Let me try bird.
进来吧
Enter.
X不是整数
X is not an integer.
X是什么？
What's x?
我要说的是 如果我在无限循环中 这将永远发生
And suffice it to say, this will happen now forever if I'm in an infinite loop
直到我尝试并成功 在这一点上我爆发了
until I try and succeed, at which point I break out.
所以让我们再试一次
So let's try again.
50 回车
50, Enter.
现在我不在圈子里了
Now I'm out of the loop.
我打印出x的实际值
And I'm printing out what x actually is.
好吧 让我暂停一下看看有没有问题
All right, let me pause here and see if there are any questions.
逻辑几乎是一样的
The logic is almost the same.
但现在不同的是我在一个循环中
But what is different now is I'm in a loop.
我在Python中使用了关键字break
And I'm using the keyword break in Python
故意跳出循环 当我
to deliberately break out of the loop when I'm
一旦用户合作 就准备好了
ready to, once the user has cooperated.
记者：我们真的需要分手吗？
AUDIENCE: Do we really need to break?
我们不能直接印出来吗
Can't we just print?
是什么让我们不只是打印？
Or what keeps us from just printing?
大卫·马兰：问得好
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
我来试试
So let me try that.
我就不能打印吗？
Couldn't I just print?
好吧 让我们看看如果我这么做会发生什么
Well, let's see what happens if I do that.
让我把最后的这行打印移动到循环中
Let me move this print line at the end into my loop
因此 缩短了程序
here, thereby shortening the program.
总的来说 这是一件好事
And, in general, that's been a good thing.
number.py的Python 输入
Python of number.py, Enter.
让我继续输入50
Let me go ahead and type in 50.
x是50
OK, x is 50.
什么是X？
What's x?
好吧 也许是49
OK, maybe it's 49.
X是49
X is 49.
好吧 也许48
OK, maybe 48.
不幸的是 我觉得 你在笑
Unfortunately, I think-- you're laughing.
你看到了
You see it.
我从来没有打破循环 这可能是一个特点
I never break out of the loop, which maybe that's a feature.
也许你想让这成为你的计划
Maybe you want this to be your program.
但我没有我
But I didn't.
我希望这场游戏最终能结束
I'd eventually like this game to stop.
所以我需要以这种方式突破
So I need to break out in that way.
但我可以做得不一样
But I can do it a little differently.
我建议我们稍微修改一下
And let me propose that we modify this a little bit.
但是 首先 关于这个语法还有其他问题吗？
But, first, any other questions on this syntax here?
让我们回到之前的版本
Let me rewind to the prior version.
“哈哈 那我就只能用一个人 一个人 一个人
AUDIENCE: Hi, can I use a break [INAUDIBLE] except and else?
例如 在另一个打印中 您可以使用打印else
For example, in another print, may you use printing the else,
你可以把指纹和break或类似的东西一起使用吗？
you can use prints together with break or something like this?
DAVID MALAN：所以你可以用break inside of loops来打破循环
DAVID MALAN: So you can use break inside of loops to break out of loops.
你可以在条件句中使用它
And you can use it inside of a conditional,
比如如果精灵或者别的
like an if, an elif, or an else.
你可以在一个try except else语句中完成
You can do it inside of a try, except, else statement to.
任何时候你陷入一个循环
Any time you're in a loop that you want to break out
你可以使用这个关键字break
of, you can use this keyword, break.
我在异常的上下文中使用它
I'm using it in the context of exceptions.
但并不局限于此
But it's not restricted to that.
我也给你看看
And let me show you, too.
它甚至不需要在其他地方
It doesn't even have to be in the else.
如果我想的话 我真的可以这么做
If I wanted to, I could actually do this.
我可以摆脱我的其他人
I could get rid of my else.
我可以回到第三行 添加另一行缩进
And I could go back to line three, add another line that's indented,
4号线 然后在这里下车
line four, and break out here.
现在 为什么这在逻辑上是可以的？
Now, why is this logically OK?
好吧 想想我现在想要做的事
Well, consider what I'm now trying to do.
我正在尝试执行第三行 并将用户的输入转换为int
I'm trying to execute line three and converting the user's input to an int.
我试着把结果从右到左存储在x中
And I'm trying to store the result from right to left in x.
如果出现问题 我们已经看到的代码
If something goes wrong, the code we've already seen
马上就要跳到第五线了
is immediately going to jump to line five
然后是六个来处理异常
and then six to handle the exception.
但如果没有出错 我的代码大概
But if nothing goes wrong, my code presumably
应该继续逐行执行
should just keep on executing line by line.
因此 从技术上讲 我可以从逻辑上断定这一点
So I could technically logically put the break here.
看看当我运行这个版本时会发生什么
And watch what happens when I run this version.
50 回车 它成功了
Python of number.py, 50, Enter, it worked.
我跳出了圈子
I broke out of the loop.
现在 哪种方式更好呢？
Now, which way is better?
老实说 在这一点上 我认为这两种情况都可能发生
Honestly, I think it could go either way at this point.
这个节目太短了 甚至连
This program is so relatively short that even
虽然我现在正试着做两件事 其中之一 休息
though I'm trying to do two things now, one of which, the break,
不会失败的
is not going to fail.
你要么破产 要么不破产
You either break or you don't.
没有来自用户的数据会影响这一点
There's no piece of data from the user that's going to influence that.
严格来说 我们不需要在那里有这两行代码
We don't strictly need to have those two lines of code there.
但只有两行字
But it's only two lines.
所以我觉得没问题
So I think it's OK.
如果你回忆起我们过去的讨论 不仅仅是关于正确性的讨论--
And if you recall our discussion in the past, not just of correctness--
代码能正常工作吗？--但是设计
does the code work as it should?-- but design,
我认为 无论哪种方式 你都可以争辩
I think you could argue it either way.
如果你更喜欢这篇文章的可读性和事实
If you prefer the readability of this and the fact
你没有其他的了 那很好
that you don't have an else, that's fine.
但是 如果您更愿意最小化如何
If, though, you prefer to minimize just how
您试图执行的许多代码行 以防出现错误
many lines of code you're trying to execute in case something goes wrong,
否则 也是一种合理的方法
the else is a reasonable approach too.
好吧 请允许我也提出建议 因为我们进一步完善了这一点
Well, allow me to propose, too, now that we refine this further.
我认为我们已经到了非常正确的地步
I think we're at the point where it's pretty darn correct.
但假设现在我发现自己的今天和明天
But suppose now that I find myself today and tomorrow
试图从用户那里获得相当多的数字
trying to get numbers from the user quite a bit.
正如我们已经看到的 如果能发明我自己的功能 那就太好了
It would be nice, as we've seen, to maybe just invent my own function,
获取int以从用户获取今天和明天以及以后的整数
get int to get an integer from the user both today and tomorrow and beyond.
而且 见鬼 也许我甚至可以和其他人分享这项功能
And, heck, maybe I can even share that function with other people.
如果他们想要编写程序 他们会从用户那里获得整数
If they want to write programs, they get integers from users.
那么我该如何着手做这件事呢？
So how might I go about doing this?
好吧 让我继续提议我们这样做
Well, let me go ahead and propose that we do this.
让我去掉打印线 但把我的大部分循环留在这里
Let me get rid of the print line but keep most of my loop here.
让我定义一个名为get int的函数 该函数目前不接受任何参数
Let me define a function called get int that takes no arguments for now.
我将继续缩进我已经编写的所有代码
And I'm going to go ahead and indent all of the code I already
在get int下面写下
wrote underneath get int.
所以现在我有一个名为get int的函数 它尝试执行以下操作
So now I have a function called get int that tries to do the following.
试着从用户那里获得它
Try to get in it from the user.
如果出现错误 并且存在值错误
If something goes wrong and there's a value error,
用x对他们大喊大叫不是整数
yell at them with x is not an integer.
否则 休息吧
Else, break.
但我想在这里做的不仅仅是打破
But it's not just breaking that I want to do here.
现在我在一个函数中 回想一下我们对返回值的讨论
Now that I'm in a function, recall our discussion of return values.
如果你正在发明你自己的功能 它在生活中的目的
If you're inventing your own function whose purpose in life
屏幕上的指纹不就像是副作用吗？
isn't just a print something on the screen like a side effect
而是还给你一个价值 还给你一个价值
but is to hand back a value, to hand you back a value,
就像我们在讨论函数时用的便利贴一样
like on that same post-it note from our discussion of functions,
那么 你需要显式地返回x
well, you need to return x explicitly.
我现在如何使用这个功能？
How do I now use this function?
好吧 一旦我们开始制作我们自己的功能
Well, as soon as we start making our own functions,
也可以方便地定义我们自己的主要功能
it tends to be convenient to define our own main function as well.
这是我们节目的主要部分
That's the main part of our program.
我会让这件事变得简单
And I'm going to keep this simple.
我现在要说 x等于得到int
I'm now going to say, x equals get int.
然后在下一行 我将从前面开始打印 引用
And then on the next line, I'm going to do that print from before, quote
不引用一句话 “x是”--在花括号里--
unquote, "x is"-- in curly braces--
“x.”
"x."
在我的程序回忆的最底层
And at the very bottom of my program recall,
我要给Main打电话 所以无论如何
I'm going to call main, so that no matter what,
在一切都定义好之后 我将调用我的Main函数
I'm invoking my main function after everything's been defined.
好吧 让我们看看这是怎么回事
Well, let's see how this works.
让我继续运行Numer.py的Python
Let me go ahead and run Python of number.py.
进来吧
Enter.
让我们输入50
Let's type in 50.
而且它似乎和以前一样奏效
And it seems to work as before.
让我们继续运行一次 这次输入cat C-A-T
Let's go ahead and run it again, typing in cat, C-A-T, this time.
X不是整数
X is not an integer.
我被提示了
And I'm being prompted.
狗 我被提示了
Dog, and I'm being prompted.
小鸟 我被提示了
Bird, and I'm being prompted.
好的 好的 好的
Fine, fine, fine.
50美元
50.
这是一个整型
That's an int.
所以它被印刷出来了
And so it is printed.
所以这里值得注意的是--我展示了几个很好的特性
So what's worth noting here-- well, I'm manifesting a couple of good properties
这里
here.
首先 我有点抽象出了获取整数的概念
One, I've kind of abstracted away this notion of getting an integer.
即使我刚刚人为地按了回车键
And even though I just artificially hit Enter
就是为了暂时隐藏这个功能--
a whole bunch of times just to hide that function for now--
它需要在那里 但我们现在不需要看到它--请注意
it needs to be there, but we don't need to see it at this point-- notice
现在 整个计划真正归结为
that now this entire program really boils down
现在只需这三行代码
to just these three lines of code now.
为什么？
Why?
因为我已经抽象了从用户那里获取int的整个过程
Because I've abstracted away that whole process of getting an int from the user
我自己的这个名为get int的新函数
into this new function of my own called get int.
但我能改进这一点吗？
But can I improve upon this?
好了 让我来撤销所有这些空行
Well, let me go and undo all of those blank lines
把这个拉起来 这样我们就可以立刻在屏幕上看到更多
and pull this up just so we can see more on the screen at once.
我可以加强GET INT的实现吗？
Can I tighten up my implementation of get int?
这是正确的
It is correct.
我声称这是正确的
I claim this is correct.
它正在处理错误
It's handling errors.
它返回x
And it's returning x.
但严格地说 我不需要写那么长的代码
But I don't, strictly speaking, need to write the code as long.
我还能做什么？
What else could I do?
好吧 让我提议 如果你在第13行所做的一切都是在破坏
Well, let me propose that if all you're doing on this line 13 is breaking
然后紧接着 根据凹痕
and then immediately after that, per the indentation,
您在第14行执行了返回x 为什么要浪费大家的时间呢？
you're executing return x on line 14, why are you wasting everyone's time?
一旦您知道准备返回值 就可以返回x
Once you know you're ready to return the value, you could just return x.
因此 在其他情况下 我可以中断并返回一个值
And so in my else, I could break out and return a value.
因此 这里也使用Return来从函数返回值
So here, too, return is used to return values from functions.
Break用于中断循环
Break is used to break out of loops.
但事实证明 回报比突破更强劲
But it turns out that return is sort of stronger than break.
它不仅会让你跳出一个循环
It will not only break you out of a loop.
它还将为您返回值
It will also return a value for you.
因此 如果你愿意的话 它只做了一次两件事
So it's doing two things for once, if you will.
但我能把它做得更紧凑吗？
But can I make this even more compact?
如果我的目标只是收紧代码 尽管它已经是正确的
If my goal is to just tighten the code up, even though it's already correct,
有没有人能想到更进一步的改进
can anyone think of a further refinement,
您以前是否用过Python语言编程？
whether you've programmed in Python before or not?
我可以将这个实现进一步缩短一点吗
Can I shorten this implementation further just a little bit,
如果只是为了减少我
if only to decrease the probability that I've
犯了一个错误 少了几行 只是
made a mistake by having fewer lines and just
让它更容易阅读 因为它更短？
make it a little easier to read because it's shorter?
有什么建议可以加强我的GET INT实现吗？
Any suggestions for tightening up my implementation of get int?
观众：您只需在尝试时返回值
AUDIENCE: You can just return the value on the try
功能 当你尝试的时候
function, when you're trying.
接受输入x 然后返回x
You take the input x and then return x.
大卫·马兰：很好
DAVID MALAN: Good.
我们可以把x调高一点
We can just return x a little higher up.
让我边走边纠正大家
And let me correct folks as we go.
这不是一个Try函数
It's not a try function.
从技术上讲 这将是一个尝试的声明
It would be a try statement, technically.
一个函数通常有一个圆括号和另一个圆括号
A function typically has a parentheses and another one.
在这种情况下 这只是一个声明
In this case, it's just a statement.
但我们可以做到这一点
But we can do exactly that.
严格来说 我不需要其他的
I don't technically need the else.
如果我真的想 我可以这么做
If I really want, I could do this.
在第9行之后 我可以在这里返回x
Right after line nine, I could return x here.
或者回想一下我们有时不必要地定义变量的讨论
Or recall our discussion of defining variables unnecessarily sometimes.
如果您立即要在此定义变量 为什么要在此定义变量
Why define a variable here if you're immediately going
在这里使用 然后再也不用了？
to use it here and then never again?
这样我们就可以避免在这里排新队了
So we could avoid a new line here.
我甚至可以避免明确定义x
And I could avoid even defining x explicitly.
我可以这么说
I could just say something like this.
我可以返回int 输入 不加引号 “什么是x？”
I could return int, input, quote unquote, "what's x?"
我可以一下子把这一切都做完
I can do it all at once.
现在 哪个更好？
Now, which is better?
我不知道
I don't know.
我的意思是 再说一次 这是理性的人可能会有分歧的地方
I mean, again, this is where reasonable people might disagree.
我认为 一方面 我们正在收紧代码
I'd argue that, on the one hand, we're tightening up the code.
我们使用的线路更少了
We're using fewer lines.
它更容易阅读 我犯错误的可能性更低
It's easier to read, lower probability that I've made a mistake.
从另一方面来说 可能理解起来有点复杂
On the other hand, it's a little more complicated to understand, perhaps.
我从哪里回来就不那么明显了
It's a little less obvious where I'm returning from.
因此 我认为无论哪种方式 都可以提出论点
So I think arguments can be made either way.
归根结底 重要的是你已经有意识地这样做了
At the end of the day, what's important is that you've done this consciously.
你已经做出了这样或那样做的决定
You've made a decision to do it this way or this way.
你可以在你的脑海中为它辩护--并不是你的答案是 呃 它奏效了
And you can justify it in your mind-- not that your answer is, eh, it worked,
所以我就不管它了
so I left it alone.
有一个很好的理由
Have a good reason.
想出一个好的理由
Come up with a good reason.
这将通过经验和实践来实现
And that will come with experience and practice.
好吧 让我向你提议 我们在这里再做一次改进
Well, let me propose to you that we make one other refinement here.
假设您发现您的程序有点嘈杂
Suppose that you're finding your programs to be a little noisy.
你不停地告诉用户 这有点令人讨厌
And it's a little obnoxious that you keep telling the user,
X不是整数
x is not an integer.
X is not an integer.
X不是整数
如果你想让事情变得更温和一点 只是提示一下 那该怎么办
What if you want to make things a little gentler and just prompt
用户再次使用相同的单词 x是什么？
the user again with the same words, what's x?
X是什么？
What is x?
What's x?
再三
Again and again.
嗯 你也可以这么做
Well, you can do that as well.
事实证明 如果您想要处理Python中的异常
And it turns out that if you want to handle an exception in Python
但你想用它做任何事情--所以你想抓住它
but you want to pass on doing anything with it-- so you want to catch it,
但你实际上想要忽略它
but you essentially want to ignore it.
你不会想打印任何东西的
You don't want to print anything.
你不会想退出这个项目的
You don't want to quit the program.
你只想默默地忽略它 就像
You just want to silently ignore it, like
如果你在一间满是人的房间里讲话 而现在轮到你说话
if you're talking in a room full of people and it's your turn to talk
你就像是 算了吧
and you're just like, pass.
他们还在呼唤你
They're still calling on you.
但你不会再做什么也不会再说什么
But you're not doing or saying anything more.
我们可以在这里将这个关键字添加到我们的代码中
Well, we can add this keyword to our code here.
让我回到我的计划上来
Let me go back to my program here.
X不是一个整数 而不是一次又一次地打印出来
And instead of printing out again and again, x is not an integer,
我可以这么做
I could just do this.
我可以继续处理这个错误
I could pass on handling the error further.
我还在追赶它
I'm still catching it.
因此 即使提到值错误 用户也不会看到可怕的消息
So the user is not going to see a scary message even mentioning value error.
我的代码正在捕捉它
My code is catching it.
但我不想说任何关于它的事
But I'm passing on saying anything about it.
我会一直跟你说的
I'm going to stay in the loop.
我将保持在循环中 并不断提示用户
I'm going to stay in the loop and keep prompting and reprompting the user
所以现在的效果看起来有点像这样
so now the effect looks a little something like this.
Numer.py的巨蟒
Python of number.py.
让我们输入cat
Let's type in cat.
再说一遍x是什么？
What's x again?
让我们输入“狗”
Let's type in dog.
再说一遍x是什么？
What's x again?
输入鸟
Type in bird.
所以它只是稍微 也许 更用户友好 你只是
So it's just a little, maybe, more user friendly and that you're just
提醒用户您想要什么
reminding the user what you want.
也许情况更糟
Maybe it's worse.
也许告诉用户原因会很有帮助
Maybe it would be helpful to tell the user why
你在一次又一次地提示他们
you're prompting them again and again.
这并不明显
It's not obvious.
因此 它可能是双向的
So it could go both ways.
但是 再说一次 这只是另一种处理这些错误的机制
But, again, it's just another mechanism, now, for handling these errors.
我们使用EXCEPT关键字来捕获特定的错误
We use the except keyword to catch a specific error.
但我们不需要处理更多的事情
But we don't have to handle it more than that.
我们可以继续做一些进一步的事情
We can just pass on doing something further.
让我在这里暂停一下 看看现在是否有任何问题需要尝试 接受 否则
Let me pause here and see if there's any questions now on try, accept, else,
还是通过？
or pass?
观众：好的 是的
AUDIENCE: OK, yeah.
不是的
No.
我想 我只是对这个想法有点好奇
I was just kind of curious, I guess, about the idea
例如 当您使用GET INT函数进行发明时
of when you were inventing with the get int function, for example.
因为我注意到 很明显 经历了这一切
Because I'm noticing, obviously, going through it
整个功能的整个逻辑和分解 虽然是真的
with the whole logic and breakdown of the entire function, while true,
做这件事
do this.
但我只是有点好奇 想详细解释一下这些凹痕
But I'm just kind of curious in elaborating with the indentations
获取更多代码
for the code more.
大卫·马兰：是的
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
因此 邀请是经过深思熟虑的
So the invitation is deliberate logically.
有些语言不需要严格的缩进
Some languages don't require as rigorous indentation.
您可以使用大括号或其他符号
You can use curly braces or other symbology
弄清楚什么与什么有关
to make clear what is associated with what.
一般来说 任何时候你在这一行上缩进一些东西--
In general, any time you indent something in Python on this line--
相反 任何时候您编写一段代码时 使用的是下面的一行代码
rather, anytime you write a code a line of code in Python that's here
它下面的线条不知何故缩进了
and the lines below it are somehow indented,
这意味着这些行以某种方式与第一行相关联
that means that those lines are somehow associated with that first line.
而且 想必这些缩进的行应该只
And, presumably, those indented lines should only
如果第一行告诉计算机这样做 则执行
be executed if the first line told the computer to do so.
那么 具体地说 这意味着什么？
So, concretely, what does this mean?
在这里的第六行 我们定义了一个名为
On line six here, we're defining a function called
不带参数的GET 冒号
get in that takes no arguments, colon.
缩进至少有四个空格的所有内容
Everything that's indented by at least four spaces
此后是该功能的一部分
hereafter is part of that function.
为什么？
Why?
这只是Python语言的设计
That's just the design of the Python language.
坦率地说 我认为设计者已经厌倦了在语言中看到非常难看的代码
Frankly, I think the designers got tired of seeing really ugly code in languages
如C、C++和Java 它们不一定对此强制缩进
like C and C++ and Java that don't necessarily enforce indentation to this
范围
extent.
所以现在它已经融入到了语言中
So now it's baked into the language.
我的年表可能有点错了
And my chronology might be a little off there.
但在以下情况下 有许多语言比Python更松散
But there's been many languages that are looser than Python when
这涉及到缩进
it comes to indentation.
第七行的缩进也很有意义
The indentation is meaningful on line seven too.
请注意 因为WHILE TRUE由四个空格缩进
Notice that because the while true is indented by four spaces.
这只是意味着它是GET INT函数的一部分
That just means it's part of the get int function.
但请注意下面的While True语句 有8个 有12个
But notice below the while true statement, there is eight, there's 12,
这里有8个空位 有12个空位
there's eight, there's 12 spaces here.
我只是在快速地数点数字
And I'm just quickly counting the dots.
这意味着我刚才突出显示的所有行
That means that all of the lines I've just highlighted
都在While循环中
are inside of that while loop.
虽然True意味着执行第8行到第11行 但潜在地
While true means to execute lines eight through 11, potentially,
一遍又一遍又一遍
again and again and again.
最后 在第八行 因为我们已经尝试并缩进了下面
And now, lastly, on line eight, because we have try and indented below
这是第九行 这只是意味着你应该尝试
it is line nine, that just means that what you should try
就是九号线上的内容
is what's on line nine.
同样 在第10行 在它下面 我们缩进了第11行
And similarly, on line 10, below it, we have indented line 11.
仅当存在值错误的异常时才应传递
You should only pass when there is an exception of a value error.
所以缩进只是表示什么与什么相关联
So the indentation just means what is associated with what.
一旦你对此感到满意 你就会
And once you get comfortable with that, you'll
请注意 缩进本身就有助于解释程序的逻辑
see that the indentation alone helps explain the logic of your program.
它有一个很棒的副作用 第二天早上对你来说
And it has a wonderful side effect that for yourself the next morning,
给你的同事、家人、朋友、老师、代码
for your colleagues, your family, your friends, your teachers, your code
其结果是可读性更强 这不是一大堆乱七八糟的文本
is much more readable as a result. It's not one big mess of a blob of text.
现在正在尝试的其他问题 除了 其他 还是通过？
Other questions now on try, except, else, or pass?
观众：是的 谢谢
AUDIENCE: Yeah, thanks.
两个问题
Two question.
问题一--一旦你说通过 呼叫者能否
Question one-- once you say pass, can the caller
还能通过系统变量或其他什么方式了解这个时代吗？
still learn anything about this era through a system variable or whatever?
问题二--习题集零引用了一些字符串方法
And question two-- problem set zero referenced some string methods,
包括数字--
including is numeric--
这与[INAUDIBLE]有什么不同吗？
is it any different to [INAUDIBLE]?
大卫·马兰：问得好
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
所以在第一个问题上 如果我以这种方式处理错误
So on the first question, if I'm handling the error in this way,
打电话的人不会知道这件事的
the caller is not going to know anything about it.
这就是我处理它的意义所在 这样主调用方或其他调用方不会知道
That's the point of my handling it, so that main or other callers don't know
从技术上讲出了什么问题
that anything technically went wrong.
关于第二个问题 数字是另一个函数
On the second question, is numeric is another function
您可以调用它 它可以查看字符串并确定
that you can call that can look at a string and determine
事实上 这是一个数字吗
is this, in fact, a number.
我可以使用这样的机械装置
I could use a mechanism like that.
我可以用一个有条件的
I could use a conditional.
如果这看起来像一个数字 则将其传递给int函数
If this looks like a number, then pass it to the int function.
然后继续并将其转换为整数
And go ahead and convert it to an integer.
这完全没问题
That's totally fine.
我通常会说 毕德式的做事方式通常是
I would generally say that the Pythonic way of doing things is often,
不管是好是坏 尝试一些事情 希望它们能奏效
for better or for worse, to try things, hope they work.
但如果它们不这样做 则处理异常
But if they don't, handle the exception.
所以其他语言更倾向于检查if、Elif、Else
So other languages are more in favor of checking if, if, if, if, elif, else,
以及所有这些条件句
and all of these conditionals.
Python倾向于更多一点的思维定势 嗯 试试吧
Python tends to be a little more of the mindset, eh, try it.
但只要确保您正在处理错误即可
But just make sure you're handling the error.
所以这将是一种毕德式的方式
So this would be the Pythonic way of doing it.
不过 你的方式--检查条件句 它是不是先是一个数字？
Your way, though-- checking with the conditional, is it a number first?--
也完全合理 如果你想走那条路的话
is totally reasonable too, if you want to go that way.
好吧 让我提出一些最后的改进意见
Well, let me propose some final refinements
对这个项目来说 这真的让事情变得更加紧张
to this program that really just kind of tighten things up,
另一个步骤 以改善这一点的实施
one additional step to improve the implementation of this
获取int函数
get int function.
让我建议我们不进行硬编码 也就是手动输入x
Let me propose that we not hard code, so to speak-- that is type manually x
到处都是
all over the place.
让我们使这个函数get int更具可重用性
Let's make this function, get int, a little more reusable.
现在 请注意 我只是在使用荣誉系统 嗯 Main
Right now, notice that I'm just kind of using the honor system that, well, main
定义了一个名为x的变量
is defining a variable called x.
Get int请求一个名为x的变量
And get int is asking for a variable called x.
但如果呼叫者Main
But it would be nice if the caller, main,
不需要知道Call-ee正在给它的变量命名什么 反之亦然
doesn't have to know what the call-ee is naming its variables and vise versa.
所以Caller--调用一个函数就是使用它
So caller-- to call a function means to use it.
调用方是使用它的函数
The caller is the function that's using it.
Call-ee就是被调用的函数
The call-ee is just the function being called.
如果我不只是希望x在两个地方是相同的 那就太好了
It would be nice if I'm not just hoping that x is the same in both places.
因此 让我提出这一点
So let me propose this.
让我建议我们实际上添加一个参数来获取int 如下所示
Let me propose that we actually add a parameter to get int, like this.
X是什么？
What's x?
也就是说 如果main想要使用get int函数
That is to say, if main wants to use the get int function,
那么main应该告诉get int函数什么
well, then main should probably tell the get int function what
提示向用户显示
prompt to show the user.
就像Python附带的输入函数一样 这取决于您
Just like the input function, recall, that comes with Python, it's up to you
传递一个提示 当用户被要求输入时 用户将看到该提示
to pass in a prompt that the user then sees when the human is asked for input.
那么 我怎么才能让这一切在这里发挥作用呢？
So how do I make this work here?
我可以深入了解我对get int的定义
I can go down to my definition of get int.
我可以说 好的 get int现在要接受一个参数
And I can say, all right, get int is going to take a parameter now,
已调用提示
called prompt.
我可以随心所欲地叫它
I could call it anything I want.
但英语中的Prompt非常不言自明
But prompt in English is pretty self-explanatory.
这意味着用户将看到的消息
It means the message the user will see.
现在 在这里 当我实际使用输入时
And now, down here, when I actually use input,
我不需要冒昧地说 x是什么？
I don't have to presumptuously say, what's x?
因为如果程序 调用者想要
Because what if the program, the caller, wants
问y或z或其他一些变量？
to ask for y or z or some other variable?
我只需传递以输入调用者提供的任何提示即可
I can just pass to input whatever prompt the caller has provided.
因此 现在我正在编写更多可重复使用的代码
So now I'm making more reusable code.
它仍然可以照旧工作
It still works just the same.
就其本身而言 我并没有改变功能
I haven't changed the functionality, per se.
但现在它更有活力了 因为现在
But now it's a little more dynamic because now
GET INT不必知道或关心所请求的变量
get int doesn't have to know or care what variable's being asked for,
他们要的是什么
what's being asked for.
它只需要知道应该向用户显示什么提示即可
It just needs to know what prompt it should show to the user.
因此 如果我现在在这里运行这个程序 再次提示number.py 输入
So if I now run this program down here, again, prompt number.py, Enter,
X是什么？
what's x?
50美元似乎仍然有效
50 still seems to work.
让我们再运行一次
Let's run it again.
让我们输入cat
Let's type in cat.
它似乎仍在发挥作用
It still seems to work.
如果我输入猫、狗、鸟或其他任何东西
And if I type in cat, dog, bird, or anything else,
它将继续用相同的提示提示我 生成这个代码
it will keep prompting me with that same prompt, making this code,
因此 这一切都更加有用
therefore, all the more usable.
现在也证明了 您甚至可以自己引发异常
Now it turns out, too, you can even raise exceptions yourself
使用了Python的RAISE关键字
using Python's raise keyword.
但下次会有更多这方面的内容
But more on that another time.
所以在接下来的几天 接下来的几周 接下来的几个月
So in the coming days, the coming weeks, the coming months,
随着您用Python编写更多的代码 您会发现错误是不可避免的
as you write more code in Python, you'll see that errors are inevitable.
有时它们是语法错误 您已经
Sometimes they're syntax errors, which you've
如果你真的想运行你的程序 那你就得修好它
got to just fix if you even want to run your program at all.
但它们可能是名称错误--例如
But they could be name errors-- for instance,
你想定义但不知何故没有定义的变量--值错误
variables that you meant to define but somehow didn't-- value errors,
可能用户不合作 为您提供了一些
where maybe the user didn't cooperate and provided you with something that
您没有预料到 或者其他可能的错误或异常的完整列表
you weren't expecting, or a whole list of other possible errors or exceptions.
但现在 希望您知道如何处理这些错误
But now, hopefully, you know how you can handle these errors
并以任何你喜欢的方式回应他们
and respond to them in any way you like.
因此 这就是我们对例外情况的看法
This, then, was our look at exceptions.
我们下次再见
And we'll see you next time.